Papers of Morris K. Udall, 1920-1995
University of Arizona Library Special Collections
Papers of Morris K. Udall, 1920-1995
MS 325
Udall, Morris K.
1200 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restriction on this collection
Biographical Note
Morris "Mo" King Udall of Tucson, Arizona was born in St. Johns, Arizona on June 15, 1922. He is the grandson of David King Udall, a noted Mormon pioneer and church leader, the son of Arizona Supreme Court Chief Justice Levi S. Udall and Louise Lee Udall and brother of former Congressman and Secretary of the Interior, Stewart Lee Udall.
He attended public schools in St. Johns, Arizona and was awarded a J.D. degree from the University of Arizona in 1949 where he served as President of the Associated Student Government and co-captain of the basketball team.
He entered the United States Army-Air Force as a private in 1942 and was discharged as a captain in 1946, having served in the Pacific Theatre.
Mo played professional basketball for one season (1948-1949) with the Denver Nuggets and is a member of the Basketball Hall of Fame.
He started a law firm with his brother, Stewart in Tucson, Arizona in 1949 and served as Pima County Attorney from 1952-1954. He served as Vice-President of the Arizona Bar Association in 1961, was a co-founder of the Bank of Tucson and the Catalina Savings and Loan Association, and served as president of the Tucson YMCA in 1960.
When his brother, Stewart resigned from the House of Representatives (District 2, Arizona) to serve as Secretary of the Interior in the Kennedy Administration, Morris K. Udall was elected to his seat in the 87th Congress (1961-1962). He served in each succeeding Congress until his resignation on May 4, 1991.
Morris K. Udall served as chairman of the U.S. House of Representatives Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs from 1977 to 1991. He also was the ranking member of the Committee on Foreign Affairs.
He was a candidate in the Democratic primaries for President in the 1976 national campaign. He was the keynote speaker at the Democratic National Convention in New York in 1980. In 1992, a special tribute was paid to Morris K. Udall by the Democratic Party at their national convention.
Chronology
1922 Born on June 15 in Saint Johns, Arizona, to Levis Stewart Udall (1891-1960) and Louise Lee (1893-1974). Siblings: Inez, Elma, Stewart, Eloise, and David "Burr". Attended school at St. Johns, doing farm work, and organizing local plays, rodeos, and mock courts. Top student in History and English. Played football and basketball, and was salutatorian of his hight school class.
1929 Loses right eye in a childhood accident.
1931 Contracts a nearly fatal case of spinal meningitis.
1938-1940 Co-captain of the St. Johns High School basketball team, also quarterbacked the football team, played trumpet in the school band, served as student body president and salutatorian, and wrote a column for the local newspaper,The Apache County Independent News. Editor of a St. Johns High School weekly paper.
1940 Entered University of Arizona in the fall on a basketball scholarship, opened barber shop in the student infirmary.
1941 Honor student.
1942-1945 Drafted and assigned to a limited service, noncombat support unit in Army Air Corps, assigned to Ft. Douglas, Utah and later to Lake Charles, Louisiana. With only two years of pre-law, he is appointed defense counsel for a black airman accused of killing a white guard while attempting to escape from a stockade. Prosecution won a death sentence; Mo later writes: "the case still haunts me." After Japanese surrender, assigned to Iwo Jima, reputed to be excellent poker player and enthusiastic basketball team organizer.
1946 Received honorary discharge in February. Obtained airplane pilot license. In the summer, helped his father to campaign for election to Arizona Supreme Court.
1947-1949 Captain of conference-winning University of Arizona basketball team. Elected president of student body. Lobbied state legislature for right to establish a co-op student gas station. With Stewart and others, attacked color bar in university campus. Served on editorial board of a college publication, The Ruptured Duck. Completes his law degree at University of Arizona. Scored highest grade on Arizona bar exam and was administered the bar oath by his father, Justice Levi Udall of the Arizona Supreme Court. Chaired Mayor's Citizen Committee on Public Housing. Played professional basketball with Denver Nuggets of National Basketball League (1948-49). Married Patricia Emery (divorced 1965), mother to his six children: Mark, Randy, Judith, Anne, Brad, and Kathy. With Stewart, established private Tucson law firm of Udall and Udall (1949-61).
1950 Appointed Chief Deputy Attorney for Pima County.
1952-1954 Elected as Pima County Attorney; investigated corruption charges at Rillito Race Track and successfully prosecuted several public officials involved.
1954 Stewart elected as representative of Arizona's Second Congressional District. Lost Pima County Superior Court Judge election.
1955 Returned to private practice, taught labor law course at University of Arizona Law School.
1956 Chaired Arizona Volunteers for Stevenson organization. Served as delegate to Democratic National Convention Served as vice chair on Arizona State Bar Commission of Criminal Law and Practice.
1958 Founding member of Bank of Tucson, appointed as vice-president and treasurer.
1960 Founder (later chairman) of Catalina Savings and Loan Association. Chairman of Modern Courts Committee of Arizona State Bar Association, directed effort to reform Arizona court system. With Stewart, organized Arizona delegates for John F. Kennedy. Wrote reference book for Arizona trial lawyers, Arizona Law of Evidence.
1961 Brother Stewart appointed as Secretary of Interior in Kennedy Administration. On March 8, 1961, Morris K. Udall won Democratic primary with 21,075 votes defeating William Hendrix, Harold Patten, H. Earl Rogge, C.J. Carreon, and William Netherton. In special election held on May 2, 1961, Morris K. Udall won Congressional District 2 seat with 50,560 votes defeating Republican Mac Matheson. Appointed to Post Office and Civil Service Committee after being sworn in by Speaker of the House Sam Rayburn on May 17, 1961.
1962 Appointed to Interior and Insular Affairs. Won regular Congressional election by defeating Richard Burke in election with 39,590 votes.
1963 In conjunction with American Political Science Association, Morris K. Udall organized an orientation session for incoming freshmen congressional members.
1964 Wrote Wilderness bill for Arizona. Served as floor whip for Democratic Study Group, an organization of House Democrats. Defeated William E. Kimball with 86,499 votes.
1965 Voted against repeal of Taft-Hartley Act. In protest over procedural actions of Chairman of Post Office Committee, helped reform committee rules and structure. Voted for right-to-work legislation.
1966 Co-authored book The Job of a Congressman. Defeated Republican Alfred McGinnis with 66,813 votes.
1967 Opposed Vietnam War in speech in Tucson before the Sunday Evening Forum on October 22. Introduced resolution to strip Adam Clayton Powell of his Chairmanship of the Education and Labor Committee, and also made unsuccessful motion to seat Powell in the new Congress. Called for consensus between California and Arizona in their fight for passage of Central Arizona Project in speech before Town Hall in Los Angeles on December, 19. Appointed to Congressional Public Land Law Review Commission and served until report complete (1970).
1968 September 30,President Johnson signs Central Arizona Project bill into law. Defeated Alfred McGinnis with 102,301 votes. Married Ella Royston Ward. Challenges House Speaker John McCormack and loses in the Democratic Caucus, 178-58.
1969 In March, received letter from Ronald Ridenhour describing "My Lai Incident" in Vietnam which instigates subsequent investigation.
1970 Runs unsuccessfully against Hale Boggs for the post of Majority Leader losing in the Democratic Caucus, 140-88. Wrote Postal Reform Bill which created a new Postal Service Corp. to replace Post Office Dept. Defeated Morris Herring with 86,760 votes.
1971 Sponsored Federal Election Campaign Act. Announced support for Ed Muskie for Democratic Presidential nominee.
1972 Chairman of Arizona delegation to Democratic National Convention. Defeated Republican Eugene Savoie with 97,616 votes. Published Education of a Congressman, edited by Robert Peabody.
1973 Chaired Interior Subcommittee on Energy and the Environment. Receives honorary Doctor of Laws Degree from the University of Arizona College of Law.
1974 Named legislator of the year by National Wildlife Federation. Udall bill to reform congressional franking privileges became law. On May 17, colleagues in House circulated petition in support of Udall's nomination as Democratic Presidential nominee. August 21, the Udall 76 Committee registered with U.S. General Accounting Office. On November 23, Udall announced his candidacy in New Hampshire. Defeated Republican Keith Dolgaard 84,491 (62%) to 51,886 (38%).
1975-1976 Campaigned for Democratic Party presidential nomination in 22 primaries, finishing second in seven, Carter wins nomination. Co-sponsored Food Stamp Reform Act. Udall bills to establish national land-use policy defeated by vetoes of Nixon and Ford. Attended Democratic Convention in New York City, gave address. Defeated Laird Guttersen (R) and Mich Emerling (L) with 88,210 votes to keep congressional seat.
1977 Congress passed Udall's Strip Mining Reclamation Act. Named Chairman of Interior and Insular Affairs Committee.
1978 Sponsored Strip-Mine control legislation which is finally passed after two similar bills were vetoed by President Ford. Defeated Thomas Richey (R), Joe Bach (L) and Betsy McDonald (SW) 56,707 (53.6%) to 46,959 (44.4%), 1,144 (1%) and 907 (.8%).
1979 Diagnosed as having Parkinson's disease.
1980 Congress passed Udall's Alaska Lands Act which doubled the size of the National Park System. Campaigned on behalf of President Jimmy Carter and gave keynote address at Democratic National Convention. Defeated Richard Huff (R) and Bill Stefanov (L) 72,570 (60.9%) to 44,708 (37.5%) and 1,799 (1.5%).
1981-1982 Secured passage of Southern Arizona Water Rights Settlement Act that outlined Indian water rights claims. Served on Hunt Commission that revised rules for 1984 Democratic primary and national conventions. Challenged authority of the Arizona legislature's redistricting plan, which he contends unfairly splinters the Hispanic vote. Legislature compromises and places more of Tucson in the 2nd Congressional District. Nuclear Waste Management Policy Act passed by Congress and signed by President Reagan. Defeated Roy Laos (R) and Jessica Sampson (I) 50, 603 (71%) to 18, 694 (26%) and 1.175 (1%).
1983 Named honorary chair of American Parkinson Disease Association.
1984 Wildness Law passed setting up eight million acres of new national forests, two million acres in Arizona. Central Arizona Project costs indexed to inflation. Announces that he will not seek the Democratic presidential nomination. Re-elected, defeating Lorenzo Torrez (People Before Profits) with 105,194 (87%) to 14,727 (12%).
1985 Udall left Post Office and Civil Service for Foreign Affairs Committee.
1986 Re-elected for 14th straight term, defeating Sheldon Clark (R) and Lorenzo Torrez (People Before Profits) with 76,425 (74%) to 24,202 (23%) and 3,600 (3%).
1988 Ella Udall dies. Re-elected to 15th term defeating Republican Joseph Sweeney 35,241 (79.1%) - 9,302 (20.9%). Publishes Too Funny To Be President.
1989 Proposed Arizona Wilderness Bill to add one million acres of land in Arizona for wilderness. Married Norma Gilbert.
1990 April 23, Honored at Earth Day ceremony at Capitol in Washington, D.C. Udall's Native American Graves Protection and Repatriation Act signed into law. Re-elected to 16th term defeating Joseph Sweeney (R) with 76,106 votes.
1991 January 6, Udall fell and is hospitalized, and later transferred to a nursing home at the Veterans Administration Medical Center. May 4, resigned from Congress for health reasons.
1992 US Congress founded the Morris K. Udall Scholarship and Excellence in National Environmental Policy Foundation
1996 Received Medal of Freedom from President Clinton
1997 Morris K. Udall Parkinson's Disease Research Act of 1997 approved.
1998 December 12, Morris K. Udall died in Washington, D.C.
Organization
This collection is organized into five subgroups.
Subgroup I: Personal Files (Boxes 1-91), 1949-1995
Subgroup II: Legislative Files ( Boxes 92-518), 1961-1990
Subgroup III: Administrative Files (Boxes 519-677), 1961-1990
Subgroup IV: Media Files (Boxes 677-755), 1961-1988
Subgroup V: Supplemental Files (Boxes 756-771), 1946-1985
Scope and Content Note
Composed of Morris K. Udall's professional and public papers that document his thirty years as a Representative from Arizona's 2nd Congressional District, his tenure as Chairman of the Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, and his campaign for the 1976 Democratic Presidential nomination.
Personal files includes biographical materials; appointment books, daily schedules and guest books; personal correspondence; campaign files which document his campaigns for local Arizona government offices, Congress, Congressional leadership posts as Speaker of the House and House Majority Leader, and his bid for the 1976 Democratic Presidential nominations; invitations and publications.
Legislative files include correspondence; bill files; legislative assistant files; committee files; voting and attendance records; staff project files; the Central Arizona Project; the Public Land Law Review Commission; the Office of Technology Assessment; Congressional Record Inserts and the Democratic Study Group. Of note are the materials pertaining to the Central Arizona Project, Alaska Lands Act, Strip Mining Act, Arizona Wilderness Act, and other legislation relating to wilderness and related environmental issues.
Administrative files include correspondence, subject files and staff files that relate to routine Congressional office matters, requests and correspondence relating to particular constituent problems or issues.
Media files include correspondence; press releases and statements; mailings, newsletters and robos; clippings; questionnaires and Freshman Seminar.
Supplemental files include memorabilia and pre- Congressional activities as a lawyer and his political activity in Pima County, Arizona.
Access Terms
Udall, Morris K. -- Archives
Udall, Morris K. -- Internet resources
United States. Congress.(87th-102nd: 1961-1991)
United States -- Alaska National Interest Lands Conservation Act
Central Arizona Project (U.S.)
Arizona Wilderness Act
Conservation of natural resources -- Government policy -- United States
Wilderness areas -- Government policy -- United States
Strip mining -- Government policy -- United States
United States -- Politics and government -- 1961-1991.
Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico)
- Subgroup I: Personal, 1940-1995
  - Biographical Files, 1940-1995
    Includes: biographical materials (oral history, transcripts, clippings, correspondence, articles).
    - St. John's High School. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - University of Arizona. 1940s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - University of Arizona, Basketball Clippings. 1940s (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Denver Nuggets Basketball. 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Personal Correspondence - Family. No Date (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    - Morris K. Udall Family Tree. No Date (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ella Udall. No Date (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
    - Wedding Congratulations. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Norma Udall. No Date (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Udall Homes. No Date (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Diary of Airplane Trip, Tucson to Mexico (Mo Udall, pilot), by RLS. Circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Arizona Bar Foundation Oral History Project (includes tape). 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Interview with Frank Ducheneaux, Legislative Assistant. 1975-1990. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Biographical Article (3) (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
    - Personal Bar Association Memberships. No Date (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Biographical: Miscellaneous, Awards, Honors. No Date (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Tributes. No Date (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - ID Cards. No Date (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cartoons. No Date (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Newsletters. No Date (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Certificates of Elections. No Date (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Campaign Materials. No Date (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Clippings: Family, Staff. 1950s (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Clippings: Family, Staff. 1960s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Clippings: Family, Staff. 1970s (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Clippings: Family, Staff. 1980s (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cliff Robertson Poem. 1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Roll Call Front Page. 1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - American Parkinson Disease Association. No Date (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - University of Arizona Sports. No Date (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Norma Udall Speech. 1995 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Point Udall. No Date (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Clippings. No Date (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Appointments and Guest Books, 1964-1986
    Boxes 5-6 contain hourly office appointments in and out of congressional office including breakfast, lunch and dinner meetings, committee meetings, hearings, and lobbyist appointments. Also contain some personal appointments books. Guest books contain holographic signatures of visitors to the office.
    - Appointment Books: Office (3 vols.). 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Appointment Books (2 vols.). 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Appointment Books (3 vols). 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
    - Appointment Books (1 vol.). 1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Appointment Books (1 vol). 1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Guest Books (4 vols.). 1964-1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Appointment Books: Office (3 vols.). 1976-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - Appointment Books: Office (3 vols.). 1976-1982 (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
    - Appointment Books: Personal (10 vols.). 1981-1990 (Box 6, Folder 7-16)
    - Appointment Books: Master Schedule (1 vol.). 1984 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Guest Books, Scheduling Memos (2 vols.). 1978, 1983-1986 (Box 6, Folder 18-20)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1961-1993
    Contains personal and legal correspondence between Morris K. Udall and friends and business associates. Includes personal requests for favors from Morris K. Udall involving federal and local agencies, family correspondence, routine business and financial matters, and legal questions about pending cases. VIP correspondence includes miscellaneous correspondence regarding upcoming bill votes, congratulations for reelection, and pledges of support from John McCormack, Carl Albert, Hubert Humphrey, Ted Kennedy, Art Buchwald, Tip O'Neill and others.
    - Airplane. No Date (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Ansel Adams Award. 1984 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Byrd, A.R. 1963-1970 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - Cantera, Sally. 1966-1970 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
    - Carter, Jimmy. 1977-1980 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Case of the Missing Painting. No Date (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Faculty Position, University of Arizona. 1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Family. 1960s (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Get Well Cards. 1975 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Humor. No Date (Box 7, Folder 12-15)
    - House Leadership Race. No Date (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Man of the Year Award. No Date (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Memberships and Associations. No Date (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Nash, Terry. No Date. (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Parkinson's Disease. No Date (Box 7, Folder 20-23)
    - Personal Correspondence. 1970 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Robertson, Cliff. 1983 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Udall Center. 1988 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Injuries, Fall. 1991 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Resignation. 1991 (Box 7, Folder 28-29)
    - Retirement. No Date (Box 7, Folder 30-32)
    - Legislative Profile, 102nd Congress. No Date (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Udall, Ella "Tiger." No Date (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Udall, Louise (Sympathy Card, Remembrance Book). No Date (Box 7, Folder 35-39)
    - Udall, Mark: Trip to India. No Date (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Udall, Norma: Letter to Speaker Foley, Mo's Retirement. No Date (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Udall, Patricia E. No Date (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Udall, Tom: Congressional Campaign, New Mexico. 1982 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Udall, Tom: Attorney General Campaign, New Mexico. 1989 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - VIP Correspondence. 1963-1991 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - Baseball. 1960s-1980s (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Pay Stubs-Benefits. 1960s-1980s (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Twentieth Anniversary - Congress. 1981 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Personal Correspondence. 1961-1968 (Box 8, Folder 8-26)
    - Personal Correspondence. 1968-1984 (Box 9, Folder 1-26)
    - Personal Correspondence. 1985-1993 (Box 10, Folder 1-8)
    - Legal Correspondence. 1962-1966 (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
    - Joke Books. No Date (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
  - Campaign Files, 1952-1990
    Arranged in three subseries: General and House of Representatives (18 boxes), Democratic Presidential Nomination, 1976 (39 boxes), and House Leadership (2 boxes) and then chronological by campaign, event, record type, or campaign organization subdivision. For detailed information on arrangement and description see each subseries and box.
    - General and House of Representatives, 1952-1990
      Chronological by campaign or event. Contains correspondence, memos, fund-raising activities, routine thank yous, polls and surveys, radio and television scripts,and activities relating to election campaigns. See also Subject files for related materials on campaigns.
      - Pima County Attorney. 1952 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Pima County Superior Court Campaign. 1954 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - House of Representatives: Primary. March 1961 (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
      - House of Representatives: Polls and Surveys. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - House of Representatives: Nomination Papers. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - House of Representatives: Campaign Correspondence. December 1960-May 1961 (Box 13, Folder 7-13)
      - House of Representatives: Special General Election. May 1961 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - House of Representatives: Mac C. Matheson. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - House of Representatives: Election TV/Radio Script. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - House of Representatives: Pete Tufts Contracts/Script. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - House of Representatives: Election Expense Accounts. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - House of Representatives: District 2 Congressional Campaign. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 19)
      - House of Representatives: Campaign Debate. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 20)
      - House of Representatives: Campaign Thank Yous. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 21)
      - House of Representatives: Talk Material. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 22)
      - House of Representatives: Press Releases. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 23)
      - House of Representatives: Future Campaigns. 1961 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - House of Representatives: Precinct Committeemen. 1961 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - House of Representatives: Brochure/Personal. 1961 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - House of Representatives: Correspondence. 1961 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - House of Representatives: Petition Signatures. 1961 (Box 14, Folder 5-8)
      - House of Representatives: Campaign Materials. 1962 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - House of Representatives: Organization Names. 1962 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - House of Representatives: Miscellaneous. 1962 (Box 14, Folder 11-12)
      - House of Representatives: Correspondence. 1962 (Box 14, Folder 13-15)
      - House of Representatives: Congratulations. 1962 (Box 14, Folder 16-17)